<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eikōn brotoloigoy, or, The picture of Titus Oates, D.D. drawn to the life, in a letter to himself.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38488</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12293184</idno>
  <idno type="VID">58935</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248550228</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31989</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12293184</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38488)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58935)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1503:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eikōn brotoloigoy, or, The picture of Titus Oates, D.D. drawn to the life, in a letter to himself.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVII [1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58935:1"/>
            <p>ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΡΟΤΟΛΟΙΓΟΥ: OR, THE PICTURE OF <hi>Titus Oates, D. D.</hi> Drawn to the LIFE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a LETTER to Himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Claudius accusat moechos Catalina Cethegum.</l>
               <bibl>Juven.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by the Booksellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster,</hi> M DCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:58935:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58935:2"/>
            <head>THE PICTURE OF <hi>Titus Oates, D. D.</hi> Drawn to the LIFE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Doctor,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOR so you dignify your self, and I shall not stand with you for a Title) you have lately oblig'd the World with Three Labour'd Pieces, being your First, Second and Third <hi>Eicon Basilikes; or, True Pictures of the late King</hi> James, <hi>drawn to the Life.</hi> Truly, Doctor, to do you Right, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the whole Draught (by a peculiar bold Stroke all the way throughout it, <hi>viz.</hi> of Railing and Berogu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at every Shadow and Dash of your Quill) to be truly your own. That singular Master-Touch of yours is so conspicuous, all through the Rough Painting, that without the Subscription of your Name, every
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58935:3"/> common Eye may find whose Pencil-work 'tis; for he that reads but three Pages, may plainly see the <hi>Delineavit Titus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confess sweet, or rather sour Doctor, you have a strange Faculty at hard Words, and paw Names; and truly, Doctor, you treat Princes with the same broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd homely Dialect, as you do all Mankind. But no matter; what you want in Civility and Good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, perhaps you have in other Qualities and Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishments: And we allow you the Ambition you have always had to be a Courtier; tho' perhaps not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so fit for a Master of the Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>But all Rallery apart, bar the Rudeness of the Stile, (and yet that's a little pardonable, as being a special Talent of your own) I heartily thank you for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. I acknowledge, from the hearty Spirit of honest Truth, you have exposed, and very justly, the false Hands at the Great Helm, through the two last Reigns of not over-fragrant Memory.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, in all the true Strokes you have made in the Picture, you have notoriously flatter'd the Painter. For in drawing of King <hi>James</hi> and his Brother, both at full Length, you have here and there dasht in some few Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaments of your own, <hi>viz.</hi> your Virtues, Innocence, Services to the Nation; together with a lamentable Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry of Wrongs, Oppression, suffering for Faith and a good Conscience, and what not; when there are Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands in the World, that believe not one of all these Qualifications, Graces, Merits, Pretensions or Titles, belong to you.</p>
            <p>This is a sort of Plain-dealing, which is sometimes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued at the Price of Jewels, and you must pardon my Freedom on this Occasion. I must confess, Doctor, these Three Pieces, in Attack against Popery and Arbitrary Power, contain a great deal of unquestion'd Truth, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58935:3"/> have highly contributed to your Reputation; and I must say this of you,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Omnia si sic</l>
               <l>Dixisses—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Had every Oracle you deliver'd, been founded upon as solid a Foundation of Veracity, no Person in the World should have been louder in your Praises, than my self; nay, this present Paper, instead of a Reprimand or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, should then have been an Eulogy and Panegyrick.</p>
            <p>Nor is there any Thing here urged, in the following Discourse I intend to have with you, with the least De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign whatever, of invalidating, lessening, or scandalizing those Collections and Memoirs (you have there so labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously compiled) of the Mis-management of the last two Reigns, Heaven knows but all too true. However, you must give me leave to tell you, That the World would be highly inclinable to set a yet greater Value upon your Works themselves, would you endeavour something more largely to set the Hand that holds the Pen, a little more to Rights with them; by washing your blemish'd Credit a little whiter in the Opinion of Mankind, at least the thinking part of Mankind; whose much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wanted Reconciliation would be highly to your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, for my own part, my natural Abhorrence and Detestation of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all its Works, is such, that I would gladly give a Lawrel to every Champion against them; insomuch, that in all due Respect to your Great Undertaking, I would have that <hi>Babylon-</hi>Monster so combated on all sides, that I am pleased to see that Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athan <hi>a Pontifex Maximus,</hi> attack'd, rather than fail, Dr. even by a <hi>Carnifex Maximus.</hi> I love and honour such darling Truths, exposed in their true Light, even from any Tongue: And as a Parallel to your own Case;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58935:4"/> we read, of Old, of Heathen Oracles, that very often deliver'd Truths, though at the same time the very Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lies, the Devil himself, spoke in them. But truly, Doctor, if an Angel of Light, instead of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of Darkness, had deliver'd those Truths, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vining Spirit that utter'd them, had render'd them a great deal more grateful Musick. The Harmony of Truth would have been much more charming from a Seraphick Trumpet, than an Infernal Organ.</p>
            <p>And now, Doctor, as you have look'd back into the Miscarriages of Princes, pray turn one Glance upon some little Peccadilios of your own. You may recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, as we all do, with a sorrowful Remembrance, that you once usher'd into the World a most dismal Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy against the Life of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. by the Hands of <hi>Grove</hi> and <hi>Pickering,</hi> for Shooting the King in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park; with a long Narrative of a whole Army of Popish Pilgrims and Black Bills from St. <hi>Iago</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> to be landed at <hi>Milford-</hi>Haven; Commissions from <hi>Paulus d' Oliva</hi> for Generals and Major-Generals, for an Army of all Papists, all ready listed against the Fall of the King; and no less than 60 thousand of them, being twice as many as there are Men, Women and Children, of <hi>Romanists,</hi> in the whole Kingdom; and all for subduing and subjecting the Protestants to the Popish Yoke: Particularly, that an infinite number of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Commissions, stampt and seal'd by Father <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread,</hi> you deliver'd with your own Hands, <hi>&amp;c. cum multis aliis,</hi> several other Discoveries, all of the same rue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Countenance.</p>
            <p>Now all this Discovery you are pleased to stile, <hi>The Testimony of Truth and a good Conscience;</hi> and yet there are Thousands and ten Thousands in little <hi>Old England,</hi> that do not believe one Syllable of all this Testimony, and that from so reasonable a Ground for their Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58935:4"/> that they look for the Cloven Foot whenever they hear it but named; especially under the Title of <hi>Truth and a good Conscience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Look ye, Doctor, I would not willingly invade your Province, <hi>viz.</hi> of Railing; but would moderately offer you some Questions relating to your <hi>quondam</hi> Evidence; which, among a hundred more upon the same fertile and copious Subject, have been often askt you, but never yet answer'd.</p>
            <p>In the first Place your Plot sets forth, That the restless Spirits of the Papists, having a design to restore their long Abdicated Religion into <hi>England,</hi> the Life of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. lay in their way; and for his Removal, a Club or Consult of Jesuits, and other Popish Emissaries, to the number of Fifty, several of them coming over from Remote and Foreign Countries, on this great Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, all met together; where the whole Result of their Meeting (which was in <hi>April,</hi> 1678.) subscribed by all their Hands, were, That <hi>Groves</hi> and <hi>Pickering</hi> should go on with their design of killing the King, <hi>viz.</hi> with their screw'd Gun and Silver Bullet.</p>
            <p>Now, Doctor, it looks very odly, That those two King-killers, who by your own Oath had been Seven Years before endeavouring to do the Execution; (but one time by having the Flint loose, another time the Gun charged with all Bullets and no Powder, and seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Blunders and Miscarriages, had never executed their Design;) should be chosen the only Engines, or Engineers, to go on with so important a Service to the Popish Cause, as the Death of a King, so impatiently waited, without one single Proposal, at so grand and chargeable a Consult from all Quarters of the World, of any other more trusty and more active Hand, for so desperate and important a Service. For the engaging Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> and the Irish Ruffians, was not till many Months after.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58935:5"/>
            <p> One very irreconcileable Blunder in this poor <hi>Picker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>'s Miscarriage: In your Narrative, Paragraph 19. you swear you saw Letters from <hi>England,</hi> to the Fathers of the English Seminary at St. <hi>Omer,</hi> in the latter End of <hi>January</hi> 1677/8. <hi>Containing an Account of one</hi> Pickering, <hi>that waits upon the Jesuits at</hi> Sommerset-House, <hi>to shoot the King in St.</hi> James<hi>'s Park, when he was at some distance from his Nobles and Attendants; but the Flint of his Pistol being somewhat loose, he did defer the Action till another Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and if he had done it, and had suffered, he should have had</hi> 3000 <hi>Masses for the Health of his Soul.</hi> And yet, at the Tryal of <hi>Pickering,</hi> you positively swore this Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage <hi>of his Flint being loose, when he had a fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, but durst not give Fire, was expresly one Day, in the</hi> March <hi>following; for which Negligence he underwent Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and had</hi> 20 <hi>Strokes of Discipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Doctor, can any thing in Nature be more strange, than that <hi>Whitebread</hi> should send the St. <hi>Omers</hi> Fathers, in <hi>January,</hi> a perfect Relation of a Crime not committed till the <hi>March</hi> following? And consequently, has not the unbelieving part of the World, a very just Ground to startle and tremble at such a <hi>Testimony of a good Conscience?</hi> as you call it, <hi>Part</hi> 3. <hi>Page</hi> 4. And would not all pitying Eyes be ready to melt into Tears, to see a King-killer Drawn, Hang'd and Quarter'd, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such a doughty Evidence, that with any reasonable Man would not pass Muster for the Proof of a Petty Larceney, the stealing of an Alchymy Spoon, or a Brass Thimble?</p>
            <p>And now, if possible to look so low, (for the Bottom on't lies in Hell) as to the whole depth of your Discovery. Here was a Papist-Plot to kill King <hi>Charles</hi> II. What was this King <hi>Charles,</hi> according to your own Picture-draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to be such an Eye-sore to the Papists, and so wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Death? Why truly, <hi>A Person as deep, in the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58935:5"/> Plot, as the Duke his Brother,</hi> [Part 3d. p. 37.] where you tell <hi>how</hi> Coleman <hi>danced a Christmas Gambel at</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn, <hi>for his great Pains in the mighty Work,</hi> [viz. <hi>subdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the pestilent Northern Heresie] your Brother, your Self, [the King and the Duke] and he had upon his Hands,</hi> Ditto, Part 3d. Page 59. <hi>The King</hi> [viz. <hi>King</hi> Charles] <hi>he was engaged for Popery and the French Interest, and Arbitrary Power, as well as your self,</hi> [speaking to King <hi>James.</hi>] Again, Page 64. <hi>You and your Party had so much Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from your Brother, who was engaged with you in the whole Popish Conspiracy, saving that of his own Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this, belike, was the Man the Papists were to Kill; but, good Heavens, for what? when he was as deep in their own Mire as his Brother, and as great a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Plotter as he; and consequently, I cannot find the want they had of his Death; and unless they were such a Pack of Cut-throats, that they lov'd Murder for the meer Letchery of Murder-sake, I cannot guess why the ungrateful Popish Villains should so inhumanely lift a Hand against so stanch a Patron and Protector. But let that pass.</p>
            <p>Well, however this King was to be destroy'd. The whole Root, Body and Branch of which Conspiracy, you give us, at length, in a Narrative, consisting of 81 Paragraphs or Depositions, being the full History of the whole Mystery of Iniquity. Mystery indeed!</p>
            <p>Now it pleas'd Heaven, or some other over-ruling Power (which is all one) to inspire <hi>Titus Otes</hi> Clerk, a great Machinator in this Conspiracy, to turn a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Convert, and discover this Plot. Accordingly, as you tell us in your Narrative, you made that Discovery to his Majesty on the 13th of <hi>August,</hi> 1678. <hi>by the Means and Introduction of that worthy and honest Gentleman Mr.</hi> Christopher Kirby. Now before you made this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58935:6"/> Discovery, you tell us, in that very Narrative, <hi>Page</hi> 18. <hi>That you had seen Packets to the Fathers at St.</hi> Omers, <hi>bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Date</hi> Jan. 1. New Stile, 1677/8. <hi>in which the Fathers were assured, that his Majesty of</hi> Great Britain <hi>was brought to that pass, that if any Malecontents among them should not prove true to their Design, his Majesty would never give Ear to their Information.</hi> Now foreseeng all this deaf Ear of the Kings, how came it about that you produced no Living Records; brought none of those <hi>Whitebread-</hi>Commissions, nor no other occular Proof to open his Eyes and Ears? Did you believe that the sight of your Mosaick Face, and a bare Oath, would convince or awaken such obstinate Deafness and Infidelity, with no other Credentials; especially when your Discovery look'd with that unaccountable Face, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Papists should have a Hand arm'd against that Life, that <hi>was so highly engag'd in their own whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Doctor, no disparagement to your politick Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, we'll allow you, for once, the only Excuse for that notorious Stupidity, <hi>viz.</hi> That you were that egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Blockhead and Blunder, as to neglect that oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of preserving any of those substantial Treason-Testimonials, that daily came through your Hands; the producing of which might have found Faith with this unbelieving King, and indeed the whole World besides, and made him sensible that the bloody Papists had Ruffians at work to knock his own Brains out, and Armies to knock out ours; and consequently have prov'd to his Face, that the Title of <hi>Saviour of the Nation,</hi> (Reverend <hi>Salamanca</hi> Doctor) stood as stanch in your Scutcheon, as <hi>Defender of the Faith in his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, but allowing that Neglect only a false Step of your Politicks, here's another most profound Piece of your Discovery. Of these 81 Paragraphs of your Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58935:6"/> here's 24 of them the Series or Business of the Plot still carrying on after that <hi>August</hi> the 13th to <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> the 7th following, in all 20 Pages of Paper. In which last part of your Narrative (and all this after your Discovery to the King) you give us the greatest Transactions and Consults of the whole Conspiracy; particularly, that very 13th of <hi>August, At Six at Night, you, the Deponent, was not designedly, but by Accident, at a Sermon, preached by</hi> John Keins, <hi>to Twelve Men, poor in Habit, yet Men of Quality, as the Deponent supposes, by their white Hands; in which Sermon was deliver'd, That Protestants and other Heretick Princes were</hi> ipso facto <hi>deposed, because such; and that it was as lawful to destroy them as an</hi> Oliver Cromwell, <hi>or any other Ʋsurper,</hi> Nar. Parag. 58. Again, <hi>August</hi> the 18th, <hi>your Doctorship was at a Consult, where Mr.</hi> Vincent Joseph, David Keymash, <hi>Mr.</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick, <hi>Mr.</hi> Colins, <hi>Mr.</hi> Fedding, <hi>Mr.</hi> Mansell, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Laumsdale, <hi>all</hi> Dominicans, <hi>met and consulted with</hi> John Keyns, <hi>Father</hi> Hartcourt, <hi>Father</hi> Fenwick, <hi>Father</hi> Wright, <hi>Father</hi> Blundell, <hi>Jesuits; about killing the King, and carrying on the Design; at which Consult the Deponent was to and fro, and afterwards employ'd by them to carry the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posals of the Consult to the Carmelites,</hi> viz. <hi>Dr.</hi> Hanson, <hi>Dr.</hi> Kimball, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Ferers, Nar. Par. 61. <hi>On</hi> Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesday <hi>the</hi> 21<hi>st of</hi> August <hi>was another Consult held by the Jesuits and</hi> Benedictines, <hi>about the Irish Affairs; and a third Consult at Mrs.</hi> Saunder<hi>'s House, of which the Doctor had notice, before the Meeting, by</hi> John Grove. <hi>Nay, the Irish Ruffians were all hired and sent down to</hi> Windsor, <hi>not till after the</hi> 13<hi>th of</hi> August, <hi>and the Doctor by at the telling out and sending the</hi> 80 l. <hi>after them, expresly the</hi> 22<hi>d of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. Besides, <hi>Conyers</hi> and <hi>Anderson</hi> were not engaged in the King's Murder till now; for <hi>Conyers,</hi> on the very same 22d of <hi>August, shew'd the Deponent his Dagger of a Foot long in the Blade, spick and span new, bought of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58935:7"/> old Cutler in</hi> Russel-street. And the same 22d <hi>the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent met Mr.</hi> Blundel, <hi>with a Bag of Fire-balls under his Arm. And the</hi> 30<hi>th following is show'd by the said</hi> Blundel, <hi>at</hi> Fenwick<hi>'s Chamber, (being invited thither to see it) a Paper sign'd by</hi> Whitebread, <hi>in the Name of the whole So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, containing a Scheme of the manner of Firing</hi> Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, Tooley-street, <hi>St.</hi> Thomas Apostle, <hi>and the King's Ships at</hi> Wapping; Par. 63. and 67. Besides, Doctor, at every turn, you are at your old Sport of Reading of Letters, Packets, Memorials; particularly on the 2d of <hi>September</hi> a <hi>Packet directed to</hi> John Grove <hi>from the Fathers at</hi> Edenburgh, <hi>to tell the Fathers here, That they had</hi> 8000 <hi>Catholicks ready to rise, when the Business grew hot, to join with the disaffected Scots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all these many Consults, and Matters transacted since the 13th of <hi>August,</hi> we find this wonderful ill For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that the Jesuits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> should Meet, Cabal, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with as much Vigour or more than ever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least Hint or Breath of a Discovery made of their Plot to his Majesty, from the 13th of <hi>August</hi> to the 4th of <hi>September. Monstrum Horrendum!</hi> Dear Sir, was the King so great a Champion of the Papists, and such a sworn Friend of his Brothers, how little soever he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved your Testimony, as not to say one Word of all this Matter to his Brother, and thereby alarm the whole Party? Could a publick Introduction of a Plot-Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverer to a King, be made without the knowledge of the Jesuits, who are the Spies of <hi>Christendom?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But grant all this possible; however, Doctor, from your return to the Jesuits, after your Protestant-Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and Discovery to the King, undoubtedly from that Day you herded with the Papists again, only as a false Brother and Spy upon them, in order to the producing some stronger Credentials of your Veracity, than a bare Oath to confirm your hitherto suspected Truth, so little
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58935:7"/> credited by the King. And if any such Plots were still carried on, why did you not stop in your Hands so trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable a Paper as the New Proposals, subscribed by so many <hi>Dominican</hi> and Jesuits Hands, and trusted in your own Custody to carry to the <hi>Carmelites?</hi> Can any thing in the World have that Face of Impudence? Nay, has the Doctor himself the Front to tell us, That had he truly received any such Treasonable Proposals, in his new State of Penitence and Conversion from Popery and Plotting, to Confession and Honesty, that he would have made his second Plot-Discovery to Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> without one Rag or Scrap of Ocular Demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when such Opportunities were offer'd him, such invincible Convictions, as even Records of Treason were thrown into his Hands, to set his whole Testimony at so fair a Light, and clear every Shadow of his hitherto misdoubted Integrity? Dear Sir, thou wert not such a Dunce nor Ideot, to let slip such an occasion: No, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Picture-Drawer, I have a better Opinion of thy Wit: If any such Treasonable Subscriptions had ever been sign'd, and thy self employ'd for the Messenger, thou that tookst such care to thrust the Five impudent <hi>Windsor-</hi>Letters, that notorious Mass of Forgery into the World, as a Crutch to thy Plot, would'st have let drop those Shadows, for this more substantial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; and not have made use of Imposture and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusion to boulster thy lame Testimony, had there been any such Thing as Truth and Honesty to set it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</p>
            <p>Well, but Matters were not carried so silently, but that [Narr. Parag. 75.] you tell us, <hi>The Deponent saw a Letter from the Provincial, specifying, That the Provincial had been inform'd of some Discovery made, at which he was somewhat surprized;</hi> Parag. 76. <hi>The same Day, at Night, the Deponent went to visit the Provincial at his Lodging,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58935:8"/> and was order'd to come again the Morning following,</hi> Par. 77. <hi>The next Morning, being the</hi> 4<hi>th of</hi> September, <hi>according to the 'foresaid Orders, he went to the Provincial; who, upon sight of him, askt him with what Face he durst look on him, since he had play'd them such a treacherous Trick? And struck him three Blows with his Stick, and a Box on the Ear, and charged him with being with the King,</hi> &amp;c. which Intelligence he had from Father <hi>Beddingfield,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now, Doctor, here's a wonderful piece of Chivalry, for a bold Knight-Errant: The Discovery having at last, with much ado, in three-Weeks time, reach'd the Ears of your Brother-Plotters, you were Master of that prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Courage as to visit the Provincial; nay, and to come again, upon Order, the next Morning. Now was not little <hi>Titus</hi> a Hero of the first Rank, that durst trust his sweet Person in the Hands of those very Men, whose Heads, Lives, nay, their whole Cause he had betray'd? Did he not expect the same <hi>Conyer</hi>'s Dagger, or <hi>Picker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>'s Gun to be turn'd against his own Heart, that before was design'd for the Kings? What Mercy could he hope from those defeated Cut-throats and Ruffians, whom he had now exposed to inevitable Gibbets and Halters? But did the tender-hearted Provincial (nay, and prepared too for the Doctor's Reception) provide nothing but a Cane to rebuke the Shoulders of a Renegado, Apostate and Traytor, to their whole Party? Could this Provincial, the very Head of a Conspiracy, against no less than the Life of Majesty, nay and of that very Prince, who had all his whole Reign been their Friend, Patron and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, now spare the Life of a poor Varlet and Miscreant, so false and treacherous to them, and upon whose Death the preservation of their own Lives so highly depended, by stopping his Mouth and hushing him silent with a Poinard? Good Heaven! How Satyr-like, hot and cold, do these Jesuits blow, to be all Fury in one Breath, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58935:8"/> all Mercy in another; all Dove, or all Serpent. Well, Doctor, bless Heaven thou escap'd'st so miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously.</p>
            <p>Besides, Doctor, to make this Romantick Caning of thine a little more stupendious. How comes it that the Grand Hinge of thy Veracity, Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi>'s Murder, should look so ruefully in the whole Face of thy Plot? When we must suppose, that the Papists so highly resented thy Discovery of their Treasons, and made their Plot such a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> as to murder a poor Innocent Gentleman, for only barely taking thy Depositions against them; and at the same time let the Discoverer himself, a Person ten thousand times more dangerous, pass and repass, safe and untouch'd, (a small Bastinado only excepted.) Can we reasonably believe, they were those virulent Bloodsuckers, as to murder a poor Justice of the Peace for only discharging his Duty? And all, God wot, to so little purpose! When instead of stiffing thy Depositions (the grand Pretension for that Murder) the Discoverer himself was suffered to Live, Range and Reign, to make the same Discovery (if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion) 40 times over again.</p>
            <p>But truly to shew that the whole Set of Discoverers, in those Days, were all Birds of one Feather: The <hi>Prance</hi> and <hi>Bedlow,</hi> an Evidence much of thy own Stamp, <hi>Neither Barrel better Herring,</hi> &amp;c. made a most lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Account of that unfortunate Gentlemans <hi>Exit;</hi> for if we'll take their own Words, nay, and their Oaths into the Bargain; they made as doleful Havock upon him, as the Two Testifying Elders upon <hi>Susannah</hi>'s Chastity, between the <hi>Mastick</hi> Tree and the <hi>Holm</hi> Tree; for they Murder'd him no less than <hi>twice</hi> over; neither at the same Hour in the Day, nor the same Chamber nor Court in <hi>Sommerset-</hi>House; nor by the same Assassinates or manner of his Murder, nor the same Hands or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance to <hi>Primrose-Hill.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58935:9"/>
            <p> But their Blunders, dear Doctor, lie not at thy Door: Thou hast enough of thy own. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dear little <hi>Oedipus</hi> answer all thy own Riddles: Tell us how all this heteregeneous Medley can be reconciled to common Sense. We heartily believe the Popish Emissaries and Tools, as black as the heaviest Dash of thy own Gall and Pen can make 'em: However, 'tis possible to bely the Devil; and he that swears falsly even against a <hi>Judas,</hi> is himself a <hi>Judas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all these hideous Incongruities, Absurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Amusements and Contradictions, that have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed your whole Testimony; in which you have over and over again been buffoon'd in almost whole Volumes, upon that copious Theme; to all which, with all the Meekness and Patience imaginable, when you have been smitten on one Cheek you have turned the other; and born it all with so profound a Silence, that, like a poor Lamb, you never so much as bleated against your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrical Persecutors; now, I say, besides all these Absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, here happens one yet more fatal Shock against your whole unhappy Foundation, <hi>viz.</hi> the greatest Prop that supported it is now taken away. For as all the Criminals in your Plot, I mean the Murdering Ones, as <hi>Groves, Pickering, Whitebread,</hi> &amp;c. with all the strongest Abjurations to their last Breath, and the very Face of Eternity, denied all Knowledge of the Fact for which they died, asserting their Innocence with Vows, Oaths and Sacraments, and all the most tremendous Assevera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, even upon all their dying Hopes of Salvation; it was all along receiv'd as an Authentick <hi>Roman</hi> Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, that their Ghostly Guides could absolve even a dying Lie, and for the good of their Cause, commission and empower their Zealots and Proselites to front Heaven it self at their very last Gasp, with Falsities, Imposture and Delusion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Doctrin well manag'd, noble
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58935:9"/> Doctor, when time was, stood you in high Service, till this late unlucky Plot against King <hi>William</hi> utterly dash'd all. For after the Discovery of Capt. <hi>Porter,</hi> Capt. <hi>Pendergrass,</hi> &amp;c. here all the dying Champions of the <hi>Assassination,</hi> instead of the old Silence in your own Evidence-Reign; on the contrary, were so far from Tongue-ty'd in their Popish Cause and Service, that they all, more or less, made a dying Confession, justified the Truth of the Charge against them for which they suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd; nay, some of them even with a dying Shame, of being concerned in so vile and despicable a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign.</p>
            <p>Now pray, worthy Sir, to ballance fairly between these two different Phenomena, in one and the same Case, as the Learned call it. A screw'd Gun against King <hi>Charles</hi> his Breast in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park, or a Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetoon against King <hi>Williams</hi> at <hi>Turnham-Green,</hi> were two Undertakings of much the same Stamp; and had there been the same Foundation of Veracity in one as the other, hang me, if I can tell why your Screw'd-Gunners should be so close, and their Musquetooners so open.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Romans</hi> ever had any such Dispensation for a dying Lie, I suppose it is still in force; for I do not hear of any new Reformation in their Church, and that their Consciences are any ways more strait-lac'd now than formerly: And therefore if there be no such dying Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions among them, (as this last Universal Ingenuity by them, plainly speaks the contrary) I am afraid that honest Captain <hi>Porter</hi> is in the Right, and the not altogether so honest Colonel <hi>Otes,</hi> is a little in the Wrong.</p>
            <p>This I am sure, That if the Good of their Popish Cause required it, and that were the Motive for a dying Falsity; the Criminals, in this last Plot, had thrice a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58935:10"/> greater occasion for a dying Denial, than any of your own executed Conspirators.</p>
            <p>In your own Popish Plot had the screw'd Gun been stanch, and the Criminals had confest any such Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy; such a Confession would not have prov'd half so pernicious to the then Duke of <hi>York,</hi> as this last Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession has done to King <hi>James,</hi> and his whole Cause. For Instance: First you, and the rest of your Brother-Swearers, never charged the Duke with any part of the Assassination of King <hi>Charles;</hi> your <hi>Groves</hi> and <hi>Pickering</hi> acted not by any Authority, Privity or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Duke. And so, at best, though perhaps a Plot for his sake, was none, of his Assent or Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. Secondly, The Duke of <hi>York</hi> was under no Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, was then safe under the Wing of a Protecting Royal Brother, an unshaken and invincible Champion in his Behalf. And lastly, The Duke of <hi>York,</hi> at that time, though under a Suspicion of Popery by his absent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from our Church, yet had then never broken Faith with the Kingdom, violated Laws, nor subverted Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, nor had any one of those Blots in his Royal Scutcheon, that have since render'd him the Universal Odium of the Nation; he was at that time under the Mask of Honour, Justice and Innocence, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently might in all probable Reason have surmounted all Dangers; and fenced against all the feeble Blows, from any such dying Confessions. But in this last Case; here was King <hi>James</hi> himself at the Bottom of this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Conspiracy. A Messenger sent over to <hi>France</hi> to him, and his Brother <hi>Lewis;</hi> and the Attacking the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in his Winter-Camp, his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission. Here was King <hi>James</hi> actually ready to back the Bloody Blow, prepared for a Descent upon the Stroke of it. And, in short, all these dying Confessions were of no less Consequence then to shake the whole Fidelity
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58935:10"/> of almost all the few Friends he had left in <hi>England,</hi> to render his future Restoration utterly impossible, the whole <hi>Jacobite</hi> Cause desperate, and the Nation suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently alarm'd against him; by opening them that lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Prospect of his Return, <hi>viz.</hi> That he, that before had so notoriously broke through all Oaths and Laws, and had now given them an Instance of his wretched, poor-spirited Condescension to Cut-throats and Ruffians for his Tools, what miserable Havock would he make, if remounted by Conquest, under the Liberty of sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing what Lives he pleas'd, and under the Shackle of no Laws at all.</p>
            <p>And to sum all; if these dying Criminals, who tho' never so guilty, yet lying under neither Wracks nor Tortures to force their Confession, so that they had it in their Power at least to die <hi>Mute;</hi> nevertheless, though Papists lay under that Obligation, belike, of discharging a dying Conscience, and speaking Truth, tho' to the utter Confusion and Ruin of their whole Party, and indeed their whole Hopes.</p>
            <p>Now worthy Doctor, or rather Doctor worthy, (take which Title you best deserve) how far this last Plot corroborates <hi>your Testimony of a good Conscience</hi> (as you phrase it) let Reason judge. Nay, I'll appeal to your Self, whether the Mute-Criminals in your Plot, or the Speaking-Ones in this, have not equally discharged their dying Consciences, and consequently not over-well vindicated your living Testimony.</p>
            <p>Now, Doctor, pray let me give you a few Remarks upon the dismal Effects of your <hi>Testimony of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.</hi> You loudly complain against Old <hi>Hodge,</hi> for the crying Mischiefs of his scurrilous Observations; <hi>That he was villanously aiming at Popery, and destroying the Church of</hi> England, <hi>notwithstanding his specious Pretences to defend it.</hi> Part 3d. Page 60.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58935:11"/>
            <p> Now, Doctor, you cannot think worse of Old <hi>Hodge,</hi> than we do; we own him a Mercinary Tool for the Popish Cause; that his Hireling-Pen was drawn Right or Wrong, for his Popish Master's Service and Interest. But pray who set up that Scribler but <hi>Titus Otes,</hi> and the rest of his Brethren, <hi>Affidavit-</hi>Men? Who found the Gall for his Ink, and Scandal for his Libels, and indeed the whole Subject for his Papers, but your Self?</p>
            <p>How many notorious Flaws and Incoherencies, did he daily find (the Subject of almost half his Volume of Scrible) in yours and your Brethrens <hi>Testimony?</hi> Who supplied him Matter to bellow so high upon the Old Tune of Forty One, <hi>viz. False Fears and Jealousies,</hi> but your self? When those very notorious Flaws, and your own whole slender Foundation of <hi>Testimony,</hi> as you call it, furnish'd him with a very reasonable Handle to lay hold of? And therefore with a great deal of Truth and Honesty (in that part at last) to tell the World, That your tall black <hi>Don Johns,</hi> your circumcised <hi>Eliots,</hi> your Bloody Pilgrims and Black Bills, your invisible Commissions, your screw'd Guns and Silver Bullets, so awkwardly handled, and the rest of your Popish Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, were not altogether so frightful, as you had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented them; and consequently, our Fears and Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, from that Quarter, were not wholly so substantial. Faith, Doctor, his Pen was but the Cats Paw, and yours the Monkeys.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, there was a Popish Plot a Foot, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate one, as <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Papers (or rather the Fragments of them, for there was not half of them found) suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently demonstrated. But as <hi>Coleman</hi> was a Plotter you light upon by chance, (for as I remember you were so little acquainted with him, that you knew not his Face by Candle-light) and his Politick Master so very dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trously
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58935:11"/> handed him out of the World, by a shameful Promise of Mercy; and very fairly stopt his Mouth with a Halter, to prevent Blabbing: By this Master<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of an Over-reach, here was the Grand Plot husht, the sensible and truly Hellish Plot-stifled; and nothing left alive but the barking Underplots, to grin and snarl.</p>
            <p>And pray what follow'd all this Din of Snarling? Why only this: The Amusements, Weaknesses and Shallowness of those very Underplots, confounded the true One. Such a Parcel of wretched Discoverers, and no less wretched Discoveries, put even Truth it self out of Countenance.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Some Truth there was, but dash'd and mix'd with Lies;</l>
               <l>To please the Fools, and puzzle all the Wise.</l>
            </q>
            <p>By this means, first, the Duke of <hi>York</hi> gain'd his Point: For there was so much of Ridicule, in this last part, as rather favour'd his Cause. For though the then Patriots of the Nation had a just Ground for the Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s Exclusion, from the true Popish Plot, sufficient to justifie their whole Proceedings; nevertheless, there were so many worthy Gentlemen, in both Houses, so stagger'd with the Invalidity of these Under-Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as perhaps not a little contributed to the Establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Succession to the Throne.</p>
            <p>It had likewise this farther unhappy Effect upon the King himself; that undoubtedly had he had any Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to do Justice to the Cries of his People, in his Brothers Exclusion; here was such a frightful <hi>Mormo</hi> of Plot-work then a foot, as was enough to stagger and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found any such Inclinations.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58935:12"/>
            <p> So that upon the whole Issue, kind Doctor, your Self and your Brother <hi>Bedlow,</hi> and the rest of your Brothers of the same Quill, instead of the Saviours of the Nation, were really the Saviours of the Duke of <hi>Yark:</hi> Instead of the Champions of the Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, were indeed the Guardians of Popery. And I so far concur with the World, that pitied and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the Severity of your <hi>Tyburn-</hi>Castigation, that nothing was either more barbarous, or more ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in King <hi>James,</hi> than that single Injustice to Dr. <hi>Otes;</hi> for he stood indebted to you more hundreds of Pounds, than you had Scores of Lashes.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, that I may do you no Wrong in laying a little more Weight upon the Two Perjuries, proved against you, and which your self make so slight of in your Third Part, Page 4th. by calling them <hi>pretended Perjuries;</hi> as suggesting they were only forged against you, to serve a Popish Turn. Pray let me ask you if you do not Arraign the whole Justice of this present Government, in calling those Perjuries only <hi>pretended</hi> Ones? For, as I remember, sometimes since, you made your Endeavours and Application to get your Taint of Perjury repealed, and to be set <hi>Rectus in Curia,</hi> which was utterly refused you: They would not so much as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten to any such Thing.</p>
            <p>Now, upon this Denial, what follows in Course, but that you were Convicted of Two Perjuries in the Last Reign; and that Conviction justified in This. For had there been Justice, Reason or Equity, in any such Repeal, undoubtedly it had never been denied you. No, Mr. <hi>Otes,</hi> a nobler Channel and Current of Honour and Justice runs thro' the whole present Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mistration, than to be deaf to the Cries of Injured Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58935:12"/> Witness the Publick Justice, done in the Repeal of the Taint against that ever-lamented truly English Worthy, the Lord <hi>Russel;</hi> as also Captain <hi>Walcot,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If therefore <hi>Titus Otes</hi> Clerk, stands Convicted of Two Perjuries, he stands <hi>justly</hi> so Convicted. Nor was your Evidence against Mr. <hi>Eliot,</hi> though not in a Court of Record, much inferiour to Perjury: Besides one particular Record of Perjury against you, set forth, at length, by your Friend <hi>Hodge,</hi> long Years before your setting up for a National Evidence, in a private Cause, under your Father <hi>Daniel</hi>'s own Country-Roof.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, give me leave to say, without the Incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that Premuni<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>viz.</hi> of Arraigning the Justice of the Nation, That <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s in the Breast of any Man, by the Charter of his English Liberty, to suspect the Evidence of a Person convict of Perjury, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to doubt the Truth of your screw'd Gun Plot, or any other part of your Discovery; especially, when it has not Reason and Sense, as well as Forehead and Oaths, to go along with it.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, there seems to be one current Argument, (I wish, in Charity to you, it were true <hi>Sterling,</hi> and would bear Touch for you) that speaks (or at least you'll make it speak) in your Behalf; which is, <hi>That if what your Swore, in your former Evidence, were not grounded upon Honesty and fair Truth; how came it to be received as such?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Really, Dr. <hi>Otes,</hi> there must go a great deal of more Sinewy Reason to convince the Judicious, than that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58935:13"/> slender Argument. In the first place, Doctor, we are all but Men, the Wisest in the World are no more; and, as such, are subject to Error. Besides, all Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Out-cries have naturally a strange Dint of Force at their first Surprize and Alarm; and even the greatest Collective Bodies of Men may sometimes be imposed upon, by an Original Novelty, whilst Imposture and Fraud may be obtruded upon them; when, upon cooler and longer Debate and Consideration, the <hi>Mormo</hi> may be detected, and the Collusion discover'd. Besides, Time and Inquiry set Matters upon a much righter Bottom: That which looks fair to Day, by Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Falsity, Forgery and Perjury, may look foul to Morrow. New Matters may so occur, that what's a Judicial Sentence one Day, in the highest Court in the World, may be Repealed to Morrow; and yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Judge nor Jury blameable. Besides, the strongest Opinion of the wisest Man, or greatest num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of such, is no Bar to any Man's second Scrutiny; nor shall one Man's Judgment or Faith, conclude mine. And to shew you that even the wisest in the World may err; Do we not read, That even <hi>Solomon</hi> himself set up Idolatry? Is it to be supposed that a Man of his unequal'd Wisdom, the particular Gift of God himself, when he indulged the High Places, and other Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Worship, was not guilty of a very great Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight?</p>
            <p>But to come a little nearer your own Case; it is not even the Universality of an Erroneous Opinion, that excuses the Error. We read, That the whole Body of the Jews, notwithstanding they had not only been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, by Miracle, in their wondrous Passage through the Red Sea; nay, were at once both Led, Fed, and Clothed, along their whole Pilgrimage through the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58935:13"/> Wilderness, by a continued Chain of Miracles, <hi>viz.</hi> Led by the Pillar of Fire by Night, and Cloud by Day: Fed by a constant Shower of Heavenly Manna; and Cloath'd by those Raiments, which, in Forty Years Travel (of the three not the least Miracle) never wore out: And yet these very People, all in a full Cry toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, upon no more than Forty Days Absence of their Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Moses;</hi> and even after all this, I may say, Immediate Communication even with God himself, wanted a Golden Calf to go before them. Nay, their other Leader <hi>Aaron</hi> was forced to comply with the Torrent, and both subscribed and assisted to the product of this Calf. And yet neither the Universality of the Popular Votes for the Calf; nay, even the Royal Subscription t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it (for so I may not improperly call the Assent of the Leading <hi>Aaron,</hi> as the then Supreme Magistrate among them) could give either Truth, Sense, or Justice, to the product of the Calf; nor did even the Assent of <hi>Aaron</hi> as a meer Compulsive One, declare his own true Belief in the Calf. He complied with Necessity, and was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by Power.</p>
            <p>Now, Doctor, for a concluding Admonition: As you have thus generously, for the Nation's Service, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged and muster'd about 40 Sheets, in Three Volumes, containing so Ample and Critical an Inquiry into the Mis-managements of Two whole Reigns; now, to crown all, look homewards, and do your Self a little Service (not all for the Publick) by retrospecting into your own short (though too long) Evidence-Reign: In which, pray be so kind to your Self, your Friends, and the whole World, as to bestow a few Hours, and Three or Four Sheets, upon your own Defence and Justification; Unravel, Answer and Confute, all these grinning Contradictions against You; <hi>For great is Truth,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58935:14"/> (if you have any on your Side) <hi>and will prevail.</hi> I assure you, Sir, 'twill be a Work highly worth your Labour: And though your near Twenty Years Silence, argues you guilty of a great Neglect of your own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Reputation, 'tis not yet too late to mend that Fault. Besides, this Vindication of your self, has a Reference to the Publick Satisfaction; and you'll oblige the Nation, nay, and the Protestant Religion it self, by washing off all Blemishes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For that unspotted Church loves neither Impostors nor Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>Therefore, dear Sir, let us beseech you to be your own Compurgator, either one way or the other, <hi>viz.</hi> by Disburthening the long Load of Reproach that has lain upon you, in clearing your Innocence: Or otherwise to be so Ingenuous and Candid, as to own your Faults. 'Tis not the first time that false Oaths have been taken, and Innocent Blood been shed: And as Perjury is but a Breach of One Commandment, as Murder of Another; the Breach of the whole Ten has been forgiven: And therefore, Doctor, despair not of Mercy; but be kind to your self, in taking the first fair Opportunity of that publick Confession and Acknowledgment, as may lay hold of an Infinite Goodness, and set you Right in a higher Court of Record, than the <hi>Kings Bench, viz.</hi> in the <hi>Book of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer/>
            <postscript>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>ONCE more I desire my Reader to be assured, That both the Author and Publisher hereof, are true and unshaken Friends to the present Government; and as real Abhorrers and Detesters both of the <hi>Romish</hi> Superstition and Interest, as the deepest Gall of even
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58935:14"/>
                  <hi>Titus</hi> his Pen can write himself. And whereas in the preceding Discourse we have taken occasion to mention the Death of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey;</hi> we desire the World to believe, That we no ways endeavour to insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, that that unhappy Gentleman kill'd himself, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well satisfied that he was basely murder'd; tho' at the same time, we cannot come up to that uncharitable Faith, that the Persons that died for it were the real Murderers; when not only the Inconsistence of the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence against them, but likewise the dying Denials of the Criminals, even under Oaths and Sacraments, so strongly confirm our Disbelief.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Fiat Lux.</p>
               </q>
               <p>May Heaven, in its due time, give a clearer Light into that Tragical Mystery.</p>
               <p>After this candid Confession of the well-meaning of the Author of this Paper, we desire the Reader to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That we are sincere Lovers of TRUTH, and as her Champions only, we have set Pen to Paper.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>